<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mery p[ro]nosticacion for the yere of Chrystes incarnacyon a thousande fyue hundreth fortye [and] foure this to pronostycate I may be bolde that wha[n] the newe yere is come gone is ye olde.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1544</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 394.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110515</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17066)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mery p[ro]nosticacion for the yere of Chrystes incarnacyon a thousande fyue hundreth fortye [and] foure this to pronostycate I may be bolde that wha[n] the newe yere is come gone is ye olde.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Middleton?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1544]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20422 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 110 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 111 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 112 -->
            <head>A mery ꝓnoſticacion</head>
            <lg>
               <l>For the yere of Chryſtes incarnacyon</l>
               <l>A thouſande fyue hundreth fortye &amp; foure</l>
               <l>This to pronoſtycate I may be bolde</l>
               <l>That wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the newe yere is come gone is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>:<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>:<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10979:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this yere for to pronoſticate</head>
               <l>It apperteyneth nat to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oole nor dodypate</l>
               <l>To pronoſtyque of the influence of this yere</l>
               <l>For thoughe they wolde they were neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nere</l>
               <l>But I ſhal tell you of this pronoſtyca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</l>
               <l>Wherin in it taketh his chefe foundacyon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the Eclyps.</head>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Whan I conſydre Ptholome I fynde</l>
               <l>That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eclyps of the ſoune doth paſſe my mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</l>
               <l>For Capricornus &amp; Aries declarynge the ſame</l>
               <l>That Cancer and Libra were out of frame</l>
               <l>Saturne and Mars ſheweth it playne</l>
               <l>The eyght day of Apryl it may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to rayne</l>
               <l>For Iupiter and Taurus when all is done</l>
               <l>Declareth a certayne Eclyps of the ſonne</l>
               <l>But Venus and Mercury by theyr operacyon</l>
               <l>Denyeth that Virgo hath any conſtyllacyon</l>
               <l>For the Eclyps of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne &amp; alſo of the Moone</l>
               <l>Shal be ſurely, I can nat tell howe ſoone</l>
               <l>Wherfore Ptholome in his Centiloquium</l>
               <l>Telleth not before what after ſhal come</l>
               <l>Therfore I pronoſtyque as nye as I can</l>
               <l>Of thynges that ſhal happen nowe and than</l>
               <l>And ſurely or the yere go about</l>
               <l>Some of them may chaunce without doubt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>☞ Of the foure quarters of this yere.</head>
               <l>Bycauſe in heuen there be many martyrs</l>
               <l>Truely this yere ſhalbe foure quarters.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10979:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 113 -->
               <l>Wynter, Pryme tyme, Somer and Harueſt</l>
               <l>But here Ptholome I fynde thou ſwarueſt</l>
               <l>For Ptholome ſheweth not wherof I wondre</l>
               <l>That Virgo is a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uaylous ſigne of thundre</l>
               <l>Venus and Iupiter be moyſte and colde</l>
               <l>Noughty ſignes for them that be olde</l>
               <l>But I ſaye yf the nynth daye of Nouembre</l>
               <l>Had fallen vpon tenth daye of Decembre</l>
               <l>It had bene a meruaylous hote yere for bees</l>
               <l>For then had the Moone ben lyke a grene cheſe</l>
               <l>Somer begyneth the fyrſt daye of Iune</l>
               <l>And they ſhal go bare for that haue no ſhewe</l>
               <l>Sometyme inclyned to be hote in the ayre</l>
               <l>Yf it be nat foule, then it ſhal be fayre</l>
               <l>For Mars and Mercury be ſygnes of heate</l>
               <l>Men ſhal nat be colde as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouge as they ſweate</l>
               <l>By the reaſon that Libra in the occidental</l>
               <l>Shal be wyndye and drye in the Eclypſal</l>
               <l>For ſaturne, and Mars, and alſo Libra</l>
               <l>Be precedent with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le, et cetera.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ Of the twelue monethes.</head>
               <l>Bycauſe that Saturne is dominator here</l>
               <l>I fynde y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ther ſhalbe twelue monethes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yere</l>
               <l>And euery moneth contaynynge foure wekes</l>
               <l>Bycauſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent they make portage with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ekes</l>
               <l>Dayes and houre ſhal nat be ſtraunge</l>
               <l>For euery moneth the Mone ſhal chaunge</l>
               <l>By Mars and Mercury ſomtyme I fynde</l>
               <l>That this yeare ſhalbe great ſtore of wynde</l>
               <l>For men and women wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue wel dynde</l>
               <l>ſhal haue no power to holde faſt behynde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10979:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
               <l>The bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalbe boſterous, byg &amp; outragious</l>
               <l>Wherfore the ayre muſt nedes be contagious</l>
               <l>And except that God worke by his great grace</l>
               <l>The wynde ſhal nat alway ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſtyli one place</l>
               <l>Sometyme the blaſtes ſhalbe pretye and ſofte</l>
               <l>And ſometyme of force they ſhal come a loft</l>
               <l>But if the blaſtes breake out, beyonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rynke</l>
               <l>The cloudes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre ſhal ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ike</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Venus and Virgo it appereth playne</l>
               <l>That enuyous perſons ſhalbe ful of diſdayne</l>
               <l>Sometyme froſt and ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etyme ſnowe</l>
               <l>And ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>etyme in the element ꝑcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a rayn bowe</l>
               <l>Sometyme myſtes with moyſtnes mutable</l>
               <l>Bycauſe that Venus in thys poynt is varyable</l>
               <l>Than the cocke crewe and than it was day</l>
               <l>Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bullocke brake loſe &amp; the rope ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e away</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of diſeaſes and ſyckeneſſes.</head>
               <l>Dyuers dyſeaſes ſhal rayne this yere</l>
               <l>Some ſhal dye, and ſome ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary here</l>
               <l>Some ſhal haue ſuch ſore payne in theyr hedes</l>
               <l>They ſhall ſlepe on benches for lacke of beddes</l>
               <l>A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon diſeaſe both in towne and cytye</l>
               <l>Shal raygne this yere, the more is the pytye</l>
               <l>Aſwell in the countre as in the cytye towne</l>
               <l>Many ſhal nat be able to chaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a crowne</l>
               <l>And ſome ſhal ſynge ſo wofull a note</l>
               <l>That they ſhal not be able to chaunge a grote</l>
               <l>Thys is bycauſe of the Eclyps of the Mone</l>
               <l>Some ſhal lope theyr potage for lack of a ſpon</l>
               <l>In the the ſomer tyme ſhalbe ſuche an heare</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10979:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 114 -->
               <l>For Saturne and Mars haue ful wel diſcuſt</l>
               <l>That in the eclyps Mercury is combuſt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ Of ſuche as be vnder the ſonne.</head>
               <l>Kynges, Prynces, and Lordes of myght</l>
               <l>This yere ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the ſonne gyue lyght</l>
               <l>Except the cloudes ſo couer her beames</l>
               <l>Or el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ſhe ſhal ſhyne in al Chriſten realmes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the Venuſtians</head>
               <l>The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Venus ſhal proſper but lytle</l>
               <l>Becauſe that lazers ſhalbe in the ſpyttle</l>
               <l>Some childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Venus ſhal burne in ſuch loue</l>
               <l>That their handes ſhalbe fyt for euery gloue</l>
               <l>Some wyl loue more than a thouſande folde</l>
               <l>But hote loue this yere wylbe ſoue colde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ Of Marcurialles</head>
               <l>Aduocates, &amp; oratours w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good pore proctors</l>
               <l>Shalbe i as good caſe as ſom honeſt doctours</l>
               <l>The eclyps declareth them to be ſuſpecte</l>
               <l>Of takynge of brybes beyng therwithin fecte</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>☞ Of Lunatiſtes.</head>
               <l>Meſſangers wyttes ſhalbe ſo farre ſpent</l>
               <l>Somtymes ſhal forget wherfore they wer ſent</l>
               <l>Marynars ſhal ſayle into many landes</l>
               <l>But ſome parchaunce ſhal ſtycke in the ſandes</l>
               <l>Yf madmen this yere be as mad as hartes</l>
               <l>Then ſhal madmen play madmens partes</l>
               <l>To declare any farther of the eclyps of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne</l>
               <l>I can do no more then I haue done</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10979:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 115 -->
               <l>The faſſyon of vs pno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ycators, euermore was</l>
               <l>To ſpeake of ſome thynges y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> neuer came to pas</l>
               <l>Therfore when yeſhal our falſholde eſpye</l>
               <l>Do nomore but gyue vs a lytle leaue to lye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of Kynges.</head>
               <l>What kynges ſhal do this yere I cannot tel</l>
               <l>For in Gods ſecretes I was neuer ſent ſo well</l>
               <l>But I truſt that Henry our moſt noble Kynge</l>
               <l>Contynually in honour ſhal floryſſhe &amp; ſprynge</l>
               <l>W<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kateryne his wyfe &amp; Prynce Edwarde his ſon</l>
               <l>And aſwell for do as they haue hetherto done</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>☞ AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
